When I was at the CIA, both as an
analyst and as an operations officer,
one of the things that I hated the most
was the United Nations General Assembly.
It takes place every single year in
September, and it brings the city to a
screeching halt. My last tour
uh in my CIA career was at the United
Nations in New York. It's hard to even
get within blocks of the US Mission to
the United Nations. It's just
ridiculous. And world leaders come from
all over the planet to give speeches
before the General Assembly.
Well, the General Assembly, as it
happens every year, is
going to take place in September. It's
also called UNGA, by the way. And these
world leaders, like they do every year,
are going to descend on New York. It's
the Super Bowl for global politics. It's
also a big deal in terms of global
drama, where international leaders love
to get the chance
to stage on the world stage.
You know, you go back and, you know, in
history, we're taught about Nikita
Khrushchev pounding his shoe on the
table at the General Assembly, or Fidel
Castro giving a 6-hour speech, or
Muammar Gaddafi coming and sleeping in a
tent in Central Park because he wanted
to be like one of the common people.
Well,
there's a major feud this year, and
that's a feud between Benjamin Netanyahu
and the mayor of New York, Zoran
Mamdani. Mamdani has been very public in
his statements over the past week or 10
days that he's [snorts] going to try to
arrest
Benjamin Netanyahu when Netanyahu
arrives in New York and turn him over to
the International Criminal Court in The
Hague. We've got a short clip of Mamdani
uh Mamdani talking about this.
>> Last question on this topic. Israel's
Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu is
perhaps planning to visit New York for
the UN General Assembly.
Uh you pledged during your campaign and
after you won um to order his arrest to
comply with the International Criminal
Court warrant.
What will happen if he comes in
September?
>> Okay, I believe that Prime Minister
Netanyahu belongs in The Hague. He's a
war criminal who has been charged by the
International Criminal Court. And
what you will find is that is an opinion
that is held by many purely because of
what his actions have wrought over these
last many years. I've also said that I
will follow the laws that we have here
in New York City
because I believe that
there is an importance in following the
law as a leader who presides over our
city and that's something that I plan to
do.
>> Meaning? I'm sorry, I don't understand
what that means.
>> Meaning that whatever the law allows me
to do in New York City, that's what we
will do, but we won't be writing our own
laws to that end.
>> What does the law allow you to do?
>> That's an active conversation with our
legal department in seeing what the
prospects are we have here in our
municipality. However, what we've seen
at the national level is a desire
sometimes to write your own laws, to go
outside of the bounds of legality.
That's not something we have an interest
in.
>> I mean, normally when people come um to
a UN General Assembly, they're granted a
sort of amnesty because it is the seat
of the United Nations. Is that what
you're thinking that you'll honor or
you're actively looking to see if
you can actually arrest him.
>> I think we are looking at all of our
legal obligations and one of them is
with regards to the United Nations, but
the other part of this is is we're we're
not talking about a personal assessment
of Benjamin Netanyahu. We're talking
about the International Criminal Court
and the fact that they have a warrant
out for this Prime Minister's arrest.
And I think it's it's important to talk
about the weight that that has as a
charge and also that as the mayor of New
York City, I'll be following the laws of
New York City.
>> So, Netanyahu fired back immediately at
Mamdani saying this, quote, "The ICC,
the International Criminal Court, is a
kangaroo court that has no jurisdiction
over Americans or Israelis. It's bogus
arrest warrant against Prime Minister
Netanyahu was issued by a disgraced
former ICC prosecutor, Karim Khan, a few
days before allegations of sexual
misconduct against him became public. It
was a clear attempt by Khan to divert
public attention and seek protection
from scrutiny." Unquote. All right.
Relax.
The ICC is not a kangaroo court. The ICC
is the International Criminal Court. The
United States and Israel do not
recognize the International Criminal
Court and are not parties to what is
called uh the Rome Convention.
So, or the Rome Yeah, the Rome
Convention. So,
Mamdani's not going to uh arrest
Benjamin Netanyahu.
This is something that he's doing for
his own his own political benefit.
That's what politics is all about. Is
Benjamin Netanyahu a war criminal? Of
course he is. Should he go to the ICC? I
believe that he should, but it's not
going to happen.
Then came another response. This one
from uh Ambassador Mike Waltz, the US uh
Ambassador to the United Nations. He
made several points uh in his comments.
He said, "Merem Mamdani, here's why your
threat to arrest PM Netanyahu in New
York City during UNGA is not going to
happen. Number one, the US is not a
party to the Rome Statute that underlies
the ICC. That's true. That's a shame,
but it's true. Number two, the UN
Headquarters Agreement grants diplomatic
protections to visiting heads of of
government." Also true. Number three,
"Head of state immunity applies." Also
true. Number four, "Federal authority
trumps any local mayor's wishes." Also
true. He He this as an episode of pure
political theater, which it is.
But, it's something that should be in
the public discourse. Americans should
be talking about whether or not Benjamin
Netanyahu is a war criminal. They should
be talking about whether or not the Iran
war is something that we should be
involved in. They should be talking
about the effects of Israeli involvement
in American politics.
I'm not even really going to point out
the irony,
the hypocrisy
that Mike Waltz is saying head of state
immunity applies to Netanyahu after the
US broke into Nicholas Maduro's home and
kidnapped the Venezuelan president in
the middle of the night and arrested him
on drug charges. We can have that
conversation as at a later time.
But, he is correct that Netanyahu's
arrest is not going to happen unless the
US president orders it, and if that were
to ever happen, all hell would break
loose. Not going to happen.